Hussain Abuwala

Waterloo, Canada

Portfolio: hussainabuwala.github.io

About Me

2+ yr software development experience. Masters in Computer Science. Motto: Stay Hungry, Stay Foolish!

Technical Skills

Programming Languages: JavaScript / ES6, Python, C, C++, TypeScript, Java, HTML, CSS, PHP, SQL.

Frameworks: Node.js, Express.js, React.js, Bootstrap, EJS, Jest.

Databases: MySQL(Relational Database), MongoDB (NoSQL), Google Firebase, Amazon S3, DynamoDB.

Tools: Git, GitHub AWS, GCP, webpack, Vite, Docker, netlify, RESTful APIs, GraphQL, Postman, Insomnia.

Skills: Front-end, Back-end, Full-Stack, Problem Solving, Communication, Detail-oriented.

Education

University of Waterloo

January. 2022 - April 2023

Master of Mathematics (MMath) in Computer Science, CGPA: 94/100

Waterloo, ON

Monash University

Feb 2016 - June 2020

Bachelor of Computer Science (Honours), CGPA: 4.0/4.0, Awarded Overall Best Graduate

Clayton, Australia

Relevant Experience

BillEase

August 2020 - August 2021

Co-Founder and Lead Full Stack Developer

Chittagong, Bangladesh

- Developed full-stack web applications with React, JavaScript for front-end & Node.js, Express.js, MySQL for back-end, to manage bills for 5 businesses, generating \$5000 in annual revenue within the first year of operation.
- Reduced data entry errors by 30% and improved overall efficiency, resulting in a 50% decrease in bill processing time for clients. Saved up to 1 hour of employees' time everyday for bill searching using SQL queries.
- Led a team of 4 software developers through the entire Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC), supporting a code-base of 3000 lines and 50 users.
- Designed and integrated data visualization features, including interactive charts and graphs, enabling clients to gain real-time insights into their bill data. Increased project revenue by \$100000.

Central Hardware Stores

November 2019 - February 2020

Software Developer Intern

Chittagong, Bangladesh

- Created and implemented core functionalities of a bill management application, enabling users to enter, store, and retrieve bill data efficiently, contributing to a 1 hour reduction in manual data entry time every day.
- Collaborated with a cross-functional team of 5 developers and designers to enhance the application's user interface, resulting in a 50% increase in user satisfaction, as measured by post-release user feedback.
- Deployed & Integrated Continuous Integration / Deployment Pipeline. Reviewed Pull Requests (PRs), and performed deep code reviews. Experienced Agile and Scrum working methodologies in an office environment.

Projects

DocClone (Code Preview) | HTML, React, Bootstrap, Socket.io, Google Firestore, Quill, Node.js, JavaScript.

• Developed an app to track user contributions when collaborating on digital documents through keystrokes, inserts, formats and deletes. This allows users with the most significant contributions to be identified.

AppliTracker (Live Preview) (Code Preview) | HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Google Firebase, React, JavaScript.

• Created a job-tracking application designed to streamline the process of job search and application process with features such as seamless sign-up / sign-in experience and document management.

Bohra Connect (Live Preview) (Code Preview) | React, Bootstrap, Firestore, Express.js, Node.js, JavaScript, Mapbox.

• Built Bohra Connect, an app designed to foster meaningful connections among members of the Bohra community through. The app allows users to create profiles and display them on a map, using markers with their desired location.

Human Resources and Sales Order Warehouse (Code Preview) Multi-fact Star Schemas, OLAP, MySQL, SQL.

• Developed a data warehouse through the process of creating an ER diagram, data cleaning, designing multi-fact star schemas, OLAP queries to perform data analysis and query optimization using access plans and query trees.